# 教大家怎么做锅巴
Let me show you how to make crispy rice crust
# 今天又学了一招
I've learnt another trick today
# 这是最快速的上浆方法
This is the fastest way of 'Shang Jiang' (coat the food with batter)
# 番茄酱要比番茄沙司要好
Tomato sauce is better than ketchup
# 桃花泛 这是大名菜
'Tao Hua Fan' (Floating peach blossom). This is a very famous dish
# 这是83年咱们中国第一次搞烹饪大赛
In 1983, it was the first time China started to organize a cooking competition
# 康乐餐厅的常静
Master Chang Jing, from Kang Le Restaurant
# 这个老师傅获得了全国的十佳厨师之一
She was rated as one of the 'Best 10 Chefs'
# 是个女性
She was female
# 而后有机会 派我去康乐餐厅去学习
Later, I was sent to Kang Le Restaurant to study cooking by chance
# 到那学的是桃花泛
At that time, I learned how to cook this dish, 'Tao Hua Fan'
# 今天我借着这机会
Today I'm taking this opportunity
# 先把这锅巴 教大家怎么做
to teach everyone how to make the crispy rice crust first
# 我们蒸了一锅米饭
We've steamed a pot of rice
# 蒸好以后别晾的太凉
After steaming, don't cool it down for too long
# 要带着热乎气 太凉了以后就粘不上了
It should still be warm. Otherwise the rice won't stick together
# 我们手上可以沾点水  把这米饭抠出来
We can wet our hands and take out the rice
# 对这个薄厚我们根据自己来掌握 别太厚
You may decide the thickness, but don't make it too thick
# 沾点水 把它压实
Dip your hands in water and press it hard
# 按的更加瓷实 已经够瓷实了
-Make the rice solid. -It's already hard enough
# 在家里还有另外一种方法 电饼铛
There's another way of making this at home. Use an electric baking pan
# 直接按在电饼铛上
Press the rice on the baking pan
# 盖盖儿的时候烤一下
Close the lid and bake it for a while
# 然后放气 再盖盖儿再烤 再放气
Then open the lid to release the steam. Then close the lid, bake it, and release the steam again
# 烤这么几次以后就把
After repeating these steps several times
# 电饼铛敞开了一晾
Open the lid and cool it down
# 等它一干巴 它就翘起来了
When it dries out, the crispy crust will curl up
# 现在按好了
Now it's done
# 在家烤了一个 用我们家的电饼铛
I made one at home using an electric baking pan
# 烤得了的 颜色金黄 焦香
It's already baked. Golden yellow, crispy, and aromatic
# 我们这烤箱已经预热了 两百三十度
The oven has been preheated at 230 degrees Celcius
# 进去烤上 烤到大约半小时
Put it in and bake it for about half an hour
# 半小时就可以关了
After half an hour, we can turn off the oven
# 关完了敞开盖 让它放放气
Then open the door to release the steam
# 然后再关上捂着再烤个十几分钟
Then close the door and bake it for another 10 to 20 minutes
# 反复的烤两次 然后就拿出来晾着了
Bake it several times. Then take it out and cool down
# 水分挥发了
In this way, the moisture will evaporate
# 桃花泛 原料都有什么 虾仁
'Tao Hua Fan'. What are the ingredients? Shrimp
# 胡萝卜 青豆
Carrot, green pea
# 这配料可以随意一点
You can be casual about these ingredients
# 也可以放点冬菇 冬笋 马蹄片
You may also use some winter mushroom, winter bamboo shoots, or water chestnut slices
# 过去这也是个很传统的一个老菜
This dish is actually a very traditional dish
# 实际上最早的原名叫什么
Its original name was
# 叫番茄锅巴虾仁 是个烩菜 烩菜就是汁多
'Crispy rice crust and shrimp with tomato sauce'. It should be a 'stewed dish' with a lot of sauce
# 你看我们这虾仁处理好了
See, we have prepared the shrimps
# 拿这个布给它蘸干水分
We use the towel to absorb the moisture
# 胡萝卜改刀 切成虾仁状的片
Cut the carrots into 'shrimp-like' slices
# 没有青豆可以用点黄瓜
If you don't have green pea, you can use cucumber instead
# 这几块够了 一会一块给它煮一下
These pieces are enough. Let's boil it later
# 小葱花 姜米 来点蒜片
Minced green onion, minced ginger, and some sliced garlic
# 这时候我们上浆虾仁
Now let's 'Jiang' (cover the food with batter) the shrimp
# 我这个上浆就比较快
The way I'm showing is a fast one
# 鸡蛋清 用不了那么多 然后加淀粉
Egg white, but not too much. Then some starch
# 这叫蛋清糊 蛋清淀粉糊
This is called 'egg white batter'. 'Egg white-starch batter'
# 专门上白汁菜的上浆的方法
Specially designed for dishes with white sauce
# 放点盐 底味
Add some salt for the basic flavor
# 看着啊 特别快
Look at this. It's very fast
# 料酒要么大爷 现在不要
-Do you need some Chinese cooking wine, Da Ye? -Not now
# 往一个方向搅拌 齐了 和匀就可以了
-Stir in one direction. Done. -Just mix it well
# 虾仁打开
Take out the shrimp
# 抓均匀 因为先把糊调好以后
-Mix it up uniformly. -If we prepare the batter first
# 特别是用什么 鱼丝鸡丝
Especially for shredded fish or chicken
# 如果说我先浆鸡丝浆鱼丝
For example, if we are going to 'jiang' (coat food with batter) shredded fish or chicken
# 你搁了淀粉 搁盐 搁了盐搁蛋清
Normally, we add starch, salt, and egg white to the food
# 要抓拌三回到四回 容易断
We need to mix it 3 or 4 times. The food will be broken
# 就把这鸡丝鱼丝给抓断了
The shredded chicken or fish will be broken into pieces
# 这是最快速的上浆方法
This is the fastest way of 'jiang' (coat food with batter)
# 抓拌以后这一定要上劲儿
You should keep stir-mixing until it becomes tough
# 干活手底下要利索 守门
-While cooking, you should do everything neatly. -That's 'guard the door'
# 来点油 好了
Add some oil. That's enough
# 这时候我们再把它抓一下 就不容易干
Now mix it again so that it doesn't dry easily
# 下锅炒的时候也容易散开
Also, the shrimps won't clump up while stir-frying
# 看看这锅巴 现在放放气 再烤会
Take a look at the rice. Now release the steam and bake it for a while again
# 焯一下水 只要一开锅就好了
-Blanch the vegetables. -It's done as soon as the water starts boiling
# 这锅巴掰碎一点 也别太碎
Break the rice crust into small pieces, but not too small
# 掰几块 十块 一人一块
How many pieces? Ten. One piece per person
# 师父来了 瞧大爷锅巴做的不错啊
-Master, you are here. -Da Ye is making nice rice crust here!
# 炝锅 来点水
Stir-fry the green onion, ginger, and garlic first. Add some water
# 番茄酱要比番茄沙司要好
Tomato sauce is better than ketchup
# 它就是番茄酱的本味
It provides the original taste of tomato
# 炒一炒 炒的颜色更加红润
Stir-fry it. The color becomes more red
# 用水激一下
Add some cold water
# 再来一碗水 这是个烩菜
One more bowl of water. This is a 'stewed dish'
# 汤汁多一点 照着一碗（水）
There should be more sauce, like a bowl (of water)
# 这个汁我们现在 颜色已经够了
The sauce is now at the right color
# 把这料放进去
Now add these ingredients
# 黄酒 做虾酒要少 不要太多 不鲜了
-Huangjiu rice wine. Less when cooking shrimps, don't add too much. -Otherwise the shrimp will lose its savory taste
# 可以坐上油了 放糖
-We can start heating the oil. -Add sugar
# 糖要多一点 甜酸 小糖醋味
Add more sugar. This dish should taste 'sweet-sour'
# 白胡椒粉 小甜酸
-White ground pepper. -'Light sweet-sour'
# 要想甜要加盐
If you want to emphasize the sweetness, add some salt
# 淀粉加水 水淀粉
Add some starch to water. -'Water starch'
# 这时候把这味定好
Now let's set the flavor
# 糖是什么 这个汁一亮 就说明这糖够了
One thing about sugar... When the sauce becomes shiny, it means there's enough sugar
# 现在这白糖也有一个缺点
But the sugar nowadays has a shortcoming
# 有的网友说 大爷搁盐搁那么多
Some friends complained like 'Da Ye added too much salt!'
# 盐不咸 糖现在也不甜
Now the salt is not salty enough. Sugar is not as sweet as in the past, either
# 搁点白醋 白醋它的酸性比较稳
Add some white vinegar. White vinegar has a stable sour taste
# 搁米醋一下锅这味就跑了 酸度不稳
If you use rice vinegar, the sour taste will be gone as soon as you add it into the wok. It's not stable
# 这味儿搁好了 先关火
The flavor is Ok. Now turn off the heat first
# 现在我先把虾仁滑出来
Now let me fry the shrimp first
# 五成热 因为咱们家里火慢
Use 50% hot oil (150 degrees Celcius). The heat is not powerful at home
# 所以油温稍微的高一点
So we use a slightly higher temperature
# 你看这倍儿漂亮
See? This is so beautiful
# 我把虾仁弄完了捞出去
I'm taking out the shrimp
# 接着倒油 炸锅巴 颜色真鲜亮
-Then add some oil and fry the rice crust. -The color is so bright and shiny
# 然后我们就开始勾芡了
Then we start thickening the sauce
# 拿出来看看这个锅巴
Let's take a look at the rice crust
# 再烤烤 烤完了出来晾着
Bake it for more time. Then take it out and chill it outside
# 大爷行啊自己烤锅巴
Da Ye, you're great. You bake the rice crust yourself?
# 油热了 高一点 要达到六成
The oil is hot. It should be hotter, like 60% hot (180 degrees Celcius)
# 你看锅巴一会啪就胀起来了
Look. The rice crust is swelling up soon
# 炸到金黄色
Fry it until golden yellow
# 看着啊
Look!
# 这叫桃花泛
This is 'Tao Hua Fan' (Floating peach blossom)
# 你看像不像盛开的桃花 一朵一朵的
See? It's like peach blossoms. Many blossoms
# 二伯 大爷我刚才偷懒回来晚点
-Er Bai. -Da Ye, sorry for coming late
# 又赶上吃了
But just the time to eat
# 刚强 来着
Gang Qiang, take this
# 真够嫩 你听
-So tender. -Listen
# 现在这个味道正好 汁完全都浸透了
Now the flavor is just right. The sauce fully penetrates (into the rice crust)
# 现在都倍儿脆
It's still extra crispy
# 锅巴太脆了 香
The rice crust is so crispy. Delicious!
# 二伯说说吧 这个版
-Er Bai, what do you think? -This version...
# 这胡萝卜 都是切的是虾米腰
The carrots are cut into the shape of shrimp
# 大爷配黄瓜的时候 也是虾米腰
Da Ye also cuts cucumbers into the shape of shrimp
# 有时候搁点马蹄 马蹄也切成虾米腰
Some times when using water chestnut, also cut into the same shape
# 搁一两刀冬菇
As well as some winter mushroom
# 马蹄更爽脆 让大家也尝尝
-The water chestnut is more crunchy. -Let everyone take a bite
# 别介啊 大爷我还没吃够呢
No hurry, Da Ye. I haven't had enough yet
# 哥儿俩又斗上了
You brothers are having a fight
# 那挺多的
(-I made 1800 yuan in that year.) -That's a lot of money!
# 相当多了
That was a lot of money
# 你像我们俩人才77块钱(每月)
We two made 77 yuan (per month) in total
# 要是一年能攒30块钱
It was already very hard for us
# 就很不容易了
to save up to 30 yuan per year
# 当时我女儿这也三岁了
My daughter was 3 years old
# 也有一些攀比
She had... some sort of vanity
# 我们住筒子楼
We were living in a tube-shaped apartment building
# 就说爸爸人家都买彩电了
She was like, 'Dad, other people are buying color TVs!'
# 咱家什么时候买
'When can we have one?'
# 当时我们店里边有很多厨师
There were a lot of chefs in our restaurant
# 中国驻外使馆工作
working abroad in Chinese embassies
# 他们回来都会带上
When they returned, they were coming back with
# 一大件两大件
One or two 'must-have's (TV, refrigerator, and washing machine) #这里我查了一下维基，没有对应的英文，但是日文维基竟然是 三種の神器 哈哈哈哈哈哈
# 三大件
Or even three of them
# 有的家就有彩电了
So some people had a color TV
# 当时我们家是黑白
We only had a black-and-white TV at that time
# 黑白电视啊
A black-and-white TV
# 所以小孩也有一些攀比的那种心态
Well, she had some vanity
# 我说很快
I said, 'soon!'
# 然后那时候我就找找电视票
Then I started to look for a 'TV coupon'
# SN最新款
The newest model of Sony
# 20寸遥控彩电
20-inch remote control TV
# 多少钱
How much was it?
# 1750
1750 yuan
# 我一听我这辛苦一年
When I heard the price, I was like, I worked so hard for a whole year
# 我挣了一千八
to make 1800 yuan
# 买一个彩电
If I buy this color TV
# 我钱没了
It's all gone
# 是吧
Right?
# 当时我老哥哥又劝我
My old pal was persuading me
# 说兄弟你要会挣钱
He said, 'Bro, you need to make money'
# 还要会花钱
'But you also need to spend it'
# 如果你要不会花钱
'If you don't spend money'
# 你就是一个守财奴
'You are a miser'
# 我一听有道理
I thought that was reasonable
# 我毅然决然的也没跟大妈商量
So I directly made my mind. I didn't even discuss with Da Ma
# 我拿着这1800块钱
I took the 1800 yuan
# 到右安门有个机电大厦
to the 'Ji Dian Building' (Building of machines and electric devices) at You An Men
# 就把彩电就搬家来了
And I bought the color TV
# 然后打了一个车
I took a taxi back
# 这1800块钱没了
And my 1800 yuan was gone
# 后来大妈知道之后
So did Da Ma have a fight with you
# 跟您吵架了吗
when she knew about this? (Nope!) #这里字幕没打上
# 然后等晚上装了电视
In the evening, the TV was set up
# 大妈一回来
Da Ma returned from work
# 咱家多一个
(Commented) "There is a ..."
# 是吧
you know
# 新鲜物
"New thing in our home!"
# 彩电搬家来了
"The color TV is here"
# 而且这彩电还是遥控的
And it could be controlled remotely!
# 那阵所有都没有遥控
No TV could be controlled remotely back then
# 等晚上没事的时候
When we were finally free at night
# 就开始说话了
We started to talk
# 聊天嘛
Chatting, you know
# 说你真敢花钱
She was like, 'You indeed spent a lot of money'
# 你这个好花一千八百块钱
'This one? You spent 1800 yuan on it'
# 是吧
Well
# 我不是说不同意
'I am not against this idea'
# 你一年也容易吗
'But this is one year of your hard work'
# 是吧
'Right?'
# 然后你连商量都不商量
'And you didn't even discuss it with me'
# 我说我商量什么
I said, 'Why should we discuss?'
# 买电视
'Buying a TV'
# 不就让孩子高兴吗
'I just want to make our kid happy'
# 人家都有了
'Other people are buying it'
# 咱家为什么没有
'Why can't we have one?'
# 所以在我们筒子楼宿舍住的时候
So when we were living in the tube-shaped apartment building
# 我率先有彩电
I was the first one to have a color TV
# 然后冰箱双缸的洗衣机
Later, I had a refrigerator, a twin tub washing machine
# 落地的电风扇
A tower fan
# 那时候都是不可求的
At that time, there was nowhere that you could buy these things
# 买这些东西都要票
Because you needed to exchange for these stuff with their coupons
# 我都有了
But I had them all
# 然后买了一个小组合音响
Then I bought a set of speakers
# 小日子反正就一天比好
My life was getting better and better
# 一天比一天红火
More and more enjoyable
# 听说您给大妈做了一辈子饭
I heard that you've been cooking for Da Ma for your life
# 就大妈基本上不做饭是吧
Does it mean that Da Ma hardly cooks, right?
# 我有一个小承诺
I promised her
# 只要我在家饭你不用管
that 'As long as I'm home, you don't need to cook'
# 所以我就在家
So if I was at home
# 我一定是不让她做
I wouldn't let her cook
# 但是我不在家的时候
But if I was not at home
# 像一些简单的饭
(She also cooked) some simple dishes
# 蒸个米饭
Like rice
# 烙个饼
or pancake
# 吃个包饺子
dumplings
# 弄个面条
or noodles
# 面条简单了
It's easy to cook noodles
# 买点面
Just buy some noodles
# 弄个什么酱油汆也好
and cook, for example, a soy sauce soup
# 西红柿鸡蛋面也好
Or stir-fried tomato with eggs
# 炸酱面也好
Or Zhajiangmian (Fried sauce noodles)
# 有时候我一炸炸好多
Sometimes I prepared a lot of fried sauce
# 就是说给她提供一些方便
to provide some convenience for her
# 她也能做一些简单的这些食物
She could also cook some simple food like this
# 总之就是大妈被您宠了一辈子
In all, you've been taking good care of Da Ma for your life
# 对不对
Right?
# 反正我们一定会向您学习
We will definitely learn from you
# 一方面是学习
On the one hand
# 向您的那种勤奋努力
We should learn from your diligence
# 今天我所学都将为我所用
like, 'What I learn today will benefit me forever'
# 然后另一方面
On the other hand
# 我们也就是在男女朋友相处
We will also learn from you how to deal with relationships
# 什么夫妻相处方面
like how to get on with our husband or wife
# 多向您和大妈学习
We should learn from you and Da Ma
# 好吧
Ok?
# 谢谢大爷
Thank you, Da Ye
# 今天就聊到这吧
Let's finish here